<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royal project: or A clear discovery of his Majesties design in the present treaty. Whereunto is annexed a seasonable caution for the Parliament of England, the Army under the command of Tho. Lord Fairfax, and all that thirst to be for ever freed from a long established course of tyranny, and to see this nation restored to its pristine glory, freedom, and tranquility. Wherein the rottenness of the present treaty, and the impossiblility of making the people thereby secure, and absolutely free, is palpably declared, and detected. / By Verity Victor.</title>
            <author>Victor, Verity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E468_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203428</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863386</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863386</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162339</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162339)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E468[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royal project: or A clear discovery of his Majesties design in the present treaty. Whereunto is annexed a seasonable caution for the Parliament of England, the Army under the command of Tho. Lord Fairfax, and all that thirst to be for ever freed from a long established course of tyranny, and to see this nation restored to its pristine glory, freedom, and tranquility. Wherein the rottenness of the present treaty, and the impossiblility of making the people thereby secure, and absolutely free, is palpably declared, and detected. / By Verity Victor.</title>
                  <author>Victor, Verity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verity Victor is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] ye 20th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, --  Baron, 1612-1671 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162339:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Royal Project: OR A clear Diſcovery of his Majeſties Deſign in the preſent Treaty.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed a ſeaſonable Caution for the Parliament of England, the Army under the Command of <hi>Tho.</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and all that thirſt to be for ever freed from a long eſtabliſhed Courſe of Tyranny, and to ſee this Nation reſtored to its priſtine Glory, Freedom, and Tranquility.</p>
            <p>Wherein the rottenneſs of the preſent Treaty, and the impoſſibility of making the People thereby ſecure, and abſolutely free, is palpably declared, and detected.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Verity Victor.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 26.24, 25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that hateth, will counterfeit with his lips, but in his heart he layeth up deceit.</p>
               <p>Though he ſpeak favorably, beleeve him not, for there are ſeven (<hi>that is,</hi> many) abominations in his heart.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Veritas non quaerit angulos.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the year 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:162339:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:162339:2"/>
            <head>For the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Army</hi> under the Command of <hi>Tho.</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and all that thirst to be for ever freed from a long eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Courſe of Tyranny, and to ſee this Nation reſtored to its priſtine Glory, Freedom and Tranquility.</head>
            <p>TO omit <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquerors</hi> own perſidiouſneſs and falſe dealing, in confounding, obfuſcating and altering the Laws and Cuſtoms of this Realm, (which were thoſe juſt and good old Laws of <hi>Ed.</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor) after he had ſolemnly<note n="*" place="margin">See Dan. Hiſt. fo. <hi>31,</hi> &amp; <hi>33.</hi> &amp; fo. <hi>36.</hi> he grants them by Chr.</note> ſworn to maintain and keep them, and of his whole progeny ſucceſſively; eſpecially of <hi>King Iohn,</hi> who was of Dr <hi>Barnards</hi> mind, that proud prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Prieſt, now juſtly Priſoner in the Fleet, that<note n="*" place="margin">See the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles exhibited againſt him this Parliament, <hi>1642.</hi> when he was Curate of Burntwood Weal in <hi>Eſſex</hi> under Dr <hi>Baker</hi>
               </note> wiſht the King had ten thouſand Turks to aſſiſt him againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.) I will come to inſtance certain late and freſh exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Princes and great men, their perjury, perfidiouſneſs, and falſe dealing with the common people in point of publique truſt and liberty; that ſo all the world may ſee, as in a glaſs, the incertainty and inſtability of building and depending on ſuch mens Oaths, Vows, Promiſes, Contracts, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:162339:3"/>
            <p>Old <hi>Chriſtianus,</hi> the late <hi>King of Denmark,</hi> endeavoring in the beginning of theſe dire Wars between the <hi>King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to ſend over a ſhip with Arms and Ammunition for the ſupply of his Nephew our now King, had the ſaid Ship and all therein taken at ſea, and made prize for the Parliament: the which old <hi>Chriſtianus</hi> reſents ſo ill, as that he purpoſeth, for this juſt fact of the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> to ſeize on the next ſhips and goods the Merchant-Adventurers of London ſhould ſend into thoſe parts; the which the provident Company foreſeeing and fearing, ſent over Commiſſioners to know the Kings mind, <hi>Whether they might ſafely trade as formerly without having their Ships or goods ſeized?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>It would be time enough to reſolve them when their ſhips came.</hi> But they preſs to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before-hand, otherwiſe their ſhips ſhould not come; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he promiſeth free Trade, and giveth an aſſurance under his hand and ſeal. Yet nevertheleſs ſo ſoon as the Merchants ſhips came, he cauſed one of them, and all the goods therein to be ceaſed at <hi>Luxſtadt,</hi> and enforced the Merchants to redeem it with 40000 <abbr>l.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Prince of Wales</hi> promiſed the <hi>States of Holland,</hi> upon his honor and Princely word, that he would not ſtop Merchants ſhips at ſea, nor any way impede Merchandizing and Traffique, if that they would give him leave to accommodate the revolted Ships, and looſe from <hi>Gory Harbor</hi> to aſſiſt his Father, (or to this effect:) How truly he kept his Promiſe and Princely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord and valued his own Honor, let all men judg, and the Merchants teſtifie. <hi>As the old Cock crows,</hi> ſaith the proverb, <hi>ſo doth the young.</hi> Why ſhall I ſtand to remember (thoſe worthy of no remembrance) the perjured perfidious Earls of <hi>Bedford</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> with many more of like tallneſs and ſtatute, both of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> and of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Truly I have obſerved, That our Nobles and Grandees have generally, of late years, had no more regard to their Oaths and Honors, then I have to my old ſlippers, or a thing of nought: Yet theſe muſt be termed honorable and honored. The old rule is, <hi>Virtus eſt unica No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas.</hi> But this is obſolete and like an old <hi>Almanack</hi> quite out of date. Thus much for the Prerogative branches and ſprigs. Now to the root, <hi>CHARLES REX.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:162339:3"/>
            <p>Did he not, in his firſt expedition into the North againſt the Scots, upon the Biſhops quarrel, conclude and aſſign Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Articles of Peace with them, and nevertheleſs ſo ſoon as he returned, diſclaimed the Agreement, and declared againſt it, and cruſed the Papers containing it to be burnt by the hands of the common Hangman, as if it had been inforced or ſurrep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titiouſly got from him; and contrary to his Agreement, raiſe Forces and march with an Army againſt them? Are theſe things already forgotten? Did he not openly ſwear upon the holy Evangeliſts, and ſolemnly promiſe, at his Coronation, to keep all the Laws and rightful Cuſtoms of this Land, and to uphold and defend the ſame? How he hath fulfilled this Oath and Promiſe, in the behalf of our Laws and Liberties, I will not determine; Let his own Party (if they can ſpeak truth) be Judges.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Iune</hi> 1642. <hi>He profeſſeth and declareth before God, and the world, that he intended not to make War againſt the Parliament,</hi> book D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c. 1 part, pa. 356. Yet in <hi>Auguſt</hi> following he ſets up his <hi>Standard</hi> at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> proclaims open War againſt them, and all thoſe Rebels and Traytors that adhere unto them, or that do any ways ayd and aſſiſt them.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Stamford</hi> 1641. He makes a Proclamation, ſtrictly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all Officers of Juſtice to put the Laws in execution againſt all Papiſts and Popiſh Recuſants, <hi>book Decl. pa.</hi> 19. And afterwards he generally entertains all the Papiſts in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the moſt inveterate and implacable Enemies of this Church and State, and ſecures and protects them in his Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, giving to ſome of them the chiefeſt places of truſt and command in his Armies, as to the<note n="*" place="margin">And was not this a diſhonor to all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant party that was with him?</note> Lord <hi>Leven</hi> his General, Sir <hi>Arthur Aſhton,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Glamorgan, Cum multis aliis,</hi> &amp;c. And at <hi>Oxford</hi> 1642. even before his face he did tolerate Maſs to be publickly ſaid and uſed in Merton Colledg Chappel, whither all, that would, might freely reſort; and who durſt except or contradict? And whereas he avows that he is grieved at his very ſoul for the calamity of his good Subiects in <hi>Ireland</hi> (I fear he meant the bloody Rebels, for ſo he calls them, as you ſhall hear afterwards) and therefore was reſolved to go in perſon to chaſtiſe thoſe wicked and deteſtable Rebels: See his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162339:4"/>Meſſage, <hi>book Decl. pa.</hi> 133. Yet did he, after order of reſtraint by both Houſes of Parliament, give Warrant under his hand for paſſing ſeveral notorious <hi>Iriſh Papiſts into Ireland,</hi> who joyned with the Rebels, and became chief Commanders in their Armies. And whereas he ſeemeth, by his paſſionate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, ſo vehemently to abhor that odious Rebellion, as that he would joyn with his Parliament to execute the utmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary vengeance on all that ſhould be diſcovered to have a hand in it, <hi>See his Declar. in book Decl. fol.</hi> 106. He not only deteined the <hi>Ear of Leiceſter</hi> from going thither from the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> as Lord Deputy choſen by them, with clothes and ſupplies, for the Proteſtants aſſiſtance; but alſo ſeized all the ſaid clothes and ſupplies to clothe his new-levyed ragged Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Soldiers: And afterwards not only remaund the Forces that the <hi>Parliament</hi> had ſent into <hi>Ireland</hi> to ſubdue the Rebels and ſo expoted the remainder of the <hi>unmaſſacred Proteſtants</hi> to deſtruction; but alſo made Peace with the Rebels (thoſe bleſſed Creatures) and called them over to aſſiſt him to deſtroy the <hi>Parliament and people of England,</hi> terming them (as I have ſaid) his <hi>good Catholique Subjests:</hi> And who were more in favor &amp; countenance with him at <hi>Oxford,</hi> then the L. <hi>Dilſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> and the L. <hi>Taff,</hi> two <hi>Cardinal Iriſh Papiſts?</hi> and the L. <hi>Taff</hi> ſince a chief General of the Rebels againſt the poor deſerted Proteſtants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but no more, leſt I turn your ſtomacks. For who and where is he that can enumerate all his lyes, falſhoods, and fallacies, or dilate his clandeſtine practices, and continued <hi>Series</hi> of conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies and treacheries, from time to time, throughout his reign, againſt this Nation? What, have we ever gotten, by him or his Country, any thing but trouble, beggery, ſlaxery and ruine? And yet we muſt idolize his perſon, and dote upon a deceitful (now moſt happily violated) union. I will only here relate, what, I well remember, <hi>Iuſtus Lypſius,</hi> that exact Obſervator, and grand Politician of his time, denotes in his Epiſtle to the Biſhop of <hi>Croia,</hi> of his Majeſties late Father King <hi>Iames.</hi> viz. <hi>Elizabetha</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Anglorum Regina abjit; Cui ſuccedit Iacobus, Scotorum Rex, ſummus ſimulandi, &amp; diſſimulandi Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex.</hi> Such a Father ſuch a Son. But when the Fox preacheth, let the Geeſe beware.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:162339:4"/>
            <p>Theſe things ſeriouſly pondered, with multitudes of other occurrences (too many here to demonſtrate) of like nature and conſequene, together with his impenitency, the virulency and indefatigability in deſtructive plots and conſpiracies of his party and adherents, and their inſatiable deſires and ſedulous endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, <hi>per fas &amp; nefas,</hi> of ruine and revenge upon the Parliament and all their friends, may ſurely ſerve for ſufficient cautions to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd the ſnares of a Treaty, <hi>(Anguis latet ſub herba,)</hi> and not to loſe that by feigned words, which we have redeemed and delivered our ſelves from, wich the expence of ſo much trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and blood, by our ſwords. What faith or truth can there be expected from him, who hath all his life-time manifeſted himſelf an Enemy to God and good men, honored and favored none but perſons unworthy and wicked, men of corrupt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and deſtructive councels, haters of the Laws, and cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillars to the Common-wealth? And is his mind and affection changed? I wiſh they were, then there were hopes. But it is too apparent (pretend he what he will, and did ever any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend alway more fairly, and intend, (as all his Acts do teſtifie) more falſly?) that he is, as he always was, and that his mind and affections are not changed. For hath he not lately ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more ſorrow and diſcontent of ſpirit for the juſt execution of two of his party, blood-thirty men, firebrands of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>(Lucas and Liſle,)</hi> who were principal Authors and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the miſery and ruine of hundreds in <hi>Colchester</hi> that never offended, then for the ſea of innocent blood, which he hath not only occaſioned, but commanded and encouraged to be ſhed both in <hi>England, Scotland, and Ireland?</hi> I will not here mention his primary deſign againſt the <hi>Iſle of Ree</hi> to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of <hi>Rochel,</hi> and all the Proteſtant intereſt in <hi>France,</hi> not his ſending a Fleet to <hi>Cales</hi> to diſhonor the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſhew the <hi>Spaniard</hi> where we could hurt him, nor his private Letters to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and many negotiations and tranſactions with <hi>Rome and Spain;</hi> to what end, the true Proteſtant party in all the three <hi>Kingdoms</hi> have wofully found.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King Edward</hi> the ſecond of this Land, a <hi>Prince</hi> more weak, then wicked; and far inferior in evil to <hi>King Charls,</hi> (for he is more wicked then weak, and ſo much the more dangerou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162339:5"/>the leſs to be truſted, by how much he is the more impowered with abilities) was<note n="*" place="margin">See Dan. Hiſt. at the end of the life &amp; reign of <hi>Ed.</hi> the <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> depoſed by the then <hi>Parliament,</hi> for far leſs miſchief and enormities by a tenth, then this our King hath committed. And nevertheleſs when that mortifying Meſſage of the Parliaments rejection of him from being any longer King, and of their election of his Son to reign in his ſtead, was told him by ſome of the Commiſſioners ſent for that purpoſe from the Parliament unto him at <hi>Killing worth Caſtle in War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick-ſhire,</hi> where he was kept Priſoner, he expreſſed that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned ſorrow for his miſgovernment, the which this obſtinate obdurate Prince never did; <hi>confeſſing how he had been miſguided (the common excuſe of wilful Princes) and done many things whereof he now repented,</hi> (but this man is ſo far from repenting of the abundance of blood he hath ſpilt, and manifold evils he hath done, that he hath lately given countenance and conſent to the ſpilling of more blood, and ſtill perſiſts in his deſtructive plots and practiſes,) <hi>the which was he to govern again he would become a new man,</hi> (did this man ever promiſe any ſuch thing?) <hi>and was moſt ſorrowful to have ſo much offended the State</hi> (this is rather ſorrowful that he hath not utterly deſtroyed the State, and cannot avenge himſelfe of them) <hi>as it ſhould thus utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject him. But yet he gave them thanks that they were ſo gracious unto him as to elect his eldeſt ſon:</hi> the which was <hi>Ed. the third,</hi> who indeed was then young. And I b leeve this example up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Father, did the Son emin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt good all his life. For of all the Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r I read of, of the race of <hi>the Conquerer</hi> that enjoyed this <hi>Crown,</hi> he was one that was moſt obſervant of the Laws and Libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of his Nation, and reigned long both fortunately and righteouſly and ſo dyed bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nored and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved: And it is obſervable, this <hi>K. Ed.</hi> the 3. when he came to years, did Juſtice on thoſe who murthered his Father; but our <hi>K.</hi> that now is, would never ſo much as d nit the <hi>Duke of Buckingham,</hi> the manifeſt murtherer of his Father, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. <hi>Mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> Omen.</hi> But to the point and the argumentative part of this ſubject.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Court Sycophants</hi> did always ſay and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that as he was a ſucceſſor to the Conqueror, he held his <hi>Crown</hi> by the ſword, and that whatſoever Charter, Law, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:162339:5"/>Statute he paſſed either for confirmation or augmentation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny immunity or benefit to his people, it was <hi>ex mera gratia,</hi> of his meer grace and favor, and not as his duty, or our due; yea, his clawback, helbred <hi>Clergy</hi> taught publikely in their pulpits, that both our perſons and eſtates were at his Majeſties diſpoſe, and that he might take whatſoever he pleaſed: Well; grant that his tenure of the <hi>Crown</hi> was by the ſword, and ſo ours by his meer will and favor, as he and ſome of his creatures have vainly conceived, and impudently aſſerted. And true it is, that the Conqueror may by the right of Conqueſt change the Laws and Cuſtoms of any Nation, and impoſe what Laws and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms he pleaſeth: yet then by the ſame Law and right of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, we having conquered the Conqueror, have not only put the Crown aagain upon our own heads, got the ſcepter into our own hands, and (to uſe Mr<note n="*" place="margin">mr. <hi>Ja. Howel</hi> is in that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe quite beſide the cuſhion; he ſhould have firſt rightly ſtated the caſe, but ſure he was either a cup too low, or a cup too high, for he loves to ſteep his brains in ſack, and then he turns antick.</note>
               <hi>Ja. Howels</hi> own phraſe, in his late printed ſimple peece of flattery, called, <hi>The Inſtruments of a King,</hi>) put the ſword to our own ſides; but have now power alſo to diſpoſe of, and to impoſe upon the King as we pleaſe, and to ſpeak plainly, (though in Court language) it is of our <hi>meer grace and favor,</hi> if that the Parliament do ſuffer him to reign upon any terms or conditions whatſoever. He put us out of protection, diſolved the Government, and diſobliged us of our allegeance and obedience to him, the day that he ſet up his ſtandard in defiance of the Nation: And, as I have been credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly enformed, he hath often ſaid, (and his obſtinacy and obtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy to the laſt declares evidently he was ſo reſolved,) that he would win it by the ſword or loſe all; the which in the effect is only thus much, that he would either rule us by power as ſlaves, or loſe all his three Kingdoms. And ſeeing that by Gods juſt hand it is come upon him according to his wiſh or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: That he hath not only forfeited all by way of equity and juſtice, but alſo loſt all by way of war and force: Why ſhould he have any thing? let it be given to one that is more worthy: At leaſt, why do we treat (or rather intreat) for our own? Why do we ſtand to word it, for that which we have ſo dearly and difficultly won and purchaſed, and is now irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocably in our own hands and commands, with him, that would never treat or parl with any purpoſe of peace, or good to this Kingdom, while he was able to hold up a ſword againſt us? Did he not alway baffle and abuſe us upon all treaties, and uſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162339:6"/>them only for the more inabling him to the proſecution and atchievement of his tyrannous deſtructive purpoſes? And are not his intentions palpably diſcovered to be the ſame at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant? Read and conſider the Letters that have of late been written by ſome of his Agents, and intercepted.</p>
            <p>Let him but get in his hand, and he will ſoon have in his head, and then how eaſily will follow his whole body, with that tail of ſcorpions which will ſoon ſting us to death. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, he ſhould repent, confeſs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe amendment, (the which I know his gracious Majeſty hath ſo much grace as to ſcorn,) let not us truſt him: What will not a diſſembling <hi>Synon</hi> feign and do to accumpliſh the ruin of <hi>Troy,</hi> when all the power of <hi>Greece</hi> could not do it? He that cannot act the Lyon muſt act the Fox. The old <hi>Maxime</hi> is in policy; Truſt not a reconciled enemy, that is, one ſo ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be, leaſt <hi>Ioah</hi> like, he ſmite thee under the fifth rib, when thou neither feareſt nor ſuſpecteſt.</p>
            <p>If a potent man had a long time kept mine inheritance from me, and would hearken to no reaſon or perſwaſion, nor be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ſtand to any referrence or abiſtrament, but put me to ſore trouble, hazard and charges, by Law to recover it: and that after I had ſo recovered it, and he could no longer hold it, he ſhould offer to treat with me about it, and deſire to have it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred: Wouldſt thou not account me a fool if I ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend? What need I then to treat what or how much I ſhould have or enjoy of that, and in what manner, which I have wholly recovered as mine own, and is wholly and ſolely in mine own power and command? Was not this tacitly, and by conſent to grant him ſtill a right where he hath none? Again;</p>
            <p>If a thief upon the way ſhould by force take thy purſe and therewith eſcape, and afterwards thou meeteſt him, and by force recovereſt thy purſe, and takeſt him captive; wouldſt thou now ſtand to diſpute the cauſe with him, whether thou ſhouldſt have all, or only part of thy money, or refer it to be debated, whether it was thine or his? ſure no. For it followeth not, that becauſe another hath ſtolen my cloak, or taken it away fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, or by force, and worn it, that therefore he is the true own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it. Again;</p>
            <p>If a Tenant wilfully forfeit his leaſe, (be his Farm never ſo good, and his priviledges never ſo great,) and the Lord make
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162339:6"/>a re-entry, may not the Lord then, if he will, juſtly let this Farm to another; or if he will be ſo favorable, becauſe he that forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted was an ancient Tenant, as to let him repoſſeſs it, may he not, if he will, increaſe his rent, diminiſh his priviledges, and impoſe upon him ſtricter terms and conditions then before? He may without doubt, and none can juſtly cenſure or condemn him.</p>
            <p>If the King muſt raign, (yet it is meet we ſhould firſt ſee a change of ſpirit in him, or elſe we do but beat down a Tyrant, and raiſe him up again,) let us propound our own Laws, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to him ſtrict limits and boundaries, and let him take his Crown, as of favor from the people, on a new agreement and ſtipulation, and be thereunto publikely, ſolemnly ſworn, and not treat with him on old terms, and lame, broken Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and grant him a right where he hath none. No, let us deal plainly and poſitively: This you ſhall do, theſe things you ſhall ſubcribe, and according to theſe Laws you ſhall rule, if you wil govern or enjoy your Crown; if not, your deſtruction is of your ſelf; we will turn to another. For let him grant the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions fully and totally. We are all in eminent hazard: For he is retaining his old poyſon &amp; his Queen, whoſe ſpirit is like her mothers, a Member of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples inconſiſtent with the Religion, Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom; wil by their Jeſuited Agents, and Machiavilian In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, ſo inſinuate &amp; deceive the people, that within a ſhort time the Parliament, if not the very next after this, ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact of ſuch Members, his friends and favorers, and this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments now enemies and opponants, that all which his Majeſty ſhall now grant and enact ſhall be reverſed and made null, and ſo we ſhall be fitted with a <hi>Colcheſter Bull.</hi> And where are we then? What courſe ſhall we take? Stand and cry, what ſhall we do? <hi>Poſt eſt occaſio calva.</hi> Let us therefore beware in time, leaſt we repent when it is too late: And what need the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their friends and Armies in this caſe, either a deceitful <hi>Pardon,</hi> or a ſtinking <hi>Act of Oblivion.</hi> To crave or receive either, in my judgment, is but to cry <hi>peccavi,</hi> and render that their cauſe inj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, which his Majeſty himſelf hath juſtified and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be juſt. Let them rather demand an Act of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification</hi> and perpetual <hi>Commemoration:</hi> Let a <hi>Pardon</hi> or <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> in this caſe, rather paſs for his Majeſty, and his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, who are herein the only offendants and tranſgreſſors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162339:7"/>the fundamental Laws and peace of the Kingdom. And this mercy (I conceive to be) more then they do demerrit: To me it is a <hi>Paradox,</hi> that we ſhould upon the rules and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of right Reaſon, and of the Law of Nature, be enforced to take up arms for ſelf-defence, and the preſervation of our lives, wives, children, eſtates, and (which is more precious and valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then all) our native liberties, againſt a tyranous, deſtructive, blood-thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſty enemy; and then after we have ſubdued him, to ſeek or accept an act of <hi>Inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>pnity,</hi> or <hi>Pardon</hi> from him, or any one. My reaſon is ſurprized: I underſtand it not; Is not this in the eyes of all judicious men to rejuſtifie the King in this caſe, and all his proceedings, and condemn our ſelves? I would have the Parliament ſeriouſly to conſider, whether the <hi>King,</hi> if he had conquered and prevailed by the ſword, would after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards admitted us to treat for our eſtates and liberties? Then it only remains to do unto him as he would have done unto us. He was dividing the skin before he had caught the Bear: For he gave divers of the Parliaments friends eſtates a way to ſome of his ruff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n Cavaliers before he had made a Conqueſt; by which it is eaſie to conclude how he would have dealt with us for the whole, if God (as bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d be his name he hath not, and I hope never will,) had delivered us up into his hands.</p>
            <p>And now I will only mind the Parliament of a wiſe ſaying and obſervation of their own concerning the King, when in their fears he had given them as ſtrong aſſurance of ſecurity, as any mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al could device or expect; and nevertheleſs at that very inſtant had he thoughts of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſipating and deſtroying them, and to them, all Parliaments, and our liberties. See book, Deels. pag. 101. 102. <hi>But it is not words,</hi> ſaith the Parliament, <hi>that can ſecure us in theſe our humble Deſires; we cannot but too well and ſorrowfully remember what gracious Meſſages we had from you this Summer, when with your privity, the bringing up of the Army, that is, the Army which was then in the North, was in agitation: We cannot but with like affections recal to our minds, how not two days before you gave directions for the above-named accuſation,</hi> (that is, the Accuſation which then was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the five Members,) <hi>and your own coming to Commons Houſe, that Houſe received from your Majeſty a gracious Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, that you would always have as much care of their priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as of your own Prerogative, and of the ſafety of them perſons
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162339:7"/>as of your own children.</hi> What could be ſaid more (eſpecially from a Prince) to aſſure? (Nor was the <hi>Lyon</hi> then half ſo provoked and inraged,) yet what then deſtruction was at that time more intended? Are theſe notorious diſſembled treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſo ſoon out of mind and remembrance? Let it never be ſaid in future ages, that this Parliament of <hi>England</hi> were at the firſt wiſe and ſagacious, and afterwards became ſtupid, blind and fooliſh.</p>
            <p>Beſides this true example of our wings own making; behold another ſince, even of yeſterday, of a brothers of his, the perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious King of <hi>Spain,</hi> with the people of <hi>Naples;</hi> who after he had granted whatſoever they demanded, together with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral pardon, (a thing much inſiſted on at this time) and obliged himſelf by ſolemn oath, and receiving of the Hoſt, or holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and all other Religious Ceremonies (as in all Popiſh Kingdoms are generally uſed in ſuch caſes,) for the true perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: Did notwithſtanding ſo ſoon as he had by theſe means recovered the chief Holds, and regained his power, put multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of the principal men of <hi>Naples,</hi> that had been moſt active and zealous for the people, and publike liberties, to death; and at preſent exerciſeth more cruelty and violence upon them then ever before. But let the <hi>Spaniard</hi> know, for all his great (as he ſuppoſeth) policy, that <hi>nil violentum, eſt perpetuum;</hi> and this very action ſhall be his ruin: And in the mean time he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be branded for a <hi>Caitif,</hi> and one denying his <hi>God</hi> to the worlds end.</p>
            <p>And have not we (notwithſtanding all theſe known Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, the abominable wickedneſs and perfideouſneſs of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and great men, and of the little faith, credence and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that is to be given to them,) a company of Members of both Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and of <hi>ſcotified London,</hi> as wicked and perfidious as any; who contrary to their truſts and duties, Oaths and Declarations, and the manifold Bonds of gratitude, that are upon them from the people, have privately complotted and conſpired, and are willing and ready, ſtudious, diligent and active, even at this inſtant, (if they can accompliſh it,) and that under the notion of this <hi>Treaty,</hi> to fell us and our poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, our lives, eſtates and liberties, to the will of a mercileſs ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcilable <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and his adherents, ſo that they can but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their own trayterous heads, and the vaſt ſums which they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162339:8"/>have purloined and ſtolen from the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> I wiſh we had no ſuch creatures; but if there be a <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>firmament,</hi> there are ſuch both in <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>City;</hi> and we ſhall never be at peace, nor proſper, until theſe <hi>Achans</hi> be brought forth unto juſtice. Albeit ſo deſperately are they wicked, that having through inſatiable converouſneſs and ambition, for want of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and the fear of God to reſtrain them, contracted to themſelves the guilt of publike ſhame and death; they had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee the whole Nation laid in aſhes, and turned into an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celdama, or ſhackled for ever in fetters of iron, then to have themſelves made publike examples, and rendered (according to their juſt demerits) a ſcorn and an abhorring to ſucceeding generations. For it is with them as with a thief beſet, who had rather kill, or be killed, then be taken. Happily I could name ſome of them, but it is needleſs, for they are already diſcovered; only I will aſſure them, that it ſhall be with them as it was with the <hi>Dove,</hi> which <hi>Noah</hi> ſent out of the Ark; ſo double and dangerous ſhall they find the <hi>King</hi> and his friends in all their ways and Councels, and the preſent ſtate of things, as that they ſhall not find whereon to reſt their feet: And let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and have always in mind how the <hi>King of Spain</hi> hath lately dealt with the Prince<note n="*" place="margin">He cut off their heads as traytors, and confiſcated their eſtates.</note>
               <hi>De Ognate,</hi> and others of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples;</hi> who receiving his rewards, and confiding in his written Grants and promiſes, did baſely and treacherouſly comply and condiſcend to re-admit his <hi>Viceroy,</hi> to the ruin of the people. A juſt guerdon for ſuch abhorred falſifyers of their truſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Traytors to their Country. But what need I go ſo far; did not <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. in his time, contrary to his faith, ſolemn pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and engagement, cauſe the <hi>Duke of Gloceſter</hi> to be baſely murihered at <hi>Callis;</hi> the <hi>Earl of Arundel</hi> to be as baſely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, and the <hi>Earl of War wick</hi> [which 3 had acted for the Publique, and ſtrongly oppoſed his tyrannous courſes,] albeit he granted him his life, to be kept priſoner all his days in the Tower of <hi>London?</hi> See the Engliſh Chronicle. And now give me leave only to relate one particle of <hi>a Spaniſh Chronicle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Vol. of the life and death of Charls the <hi>5</hi> K. of <hi>Spain,</hi> written by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Prudent Sandival.</hi>
               </note> and I will conclude, and leave all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have here rudely penned, to the <hi>application and ſerious conſideration</hi> of all judicious &amp; unbiaſſed judgments.</p>
            <p>In the yeer 1519. in the Reign of turbulent <hi>Charles,</hi> the fifth <hi>King of Spain,</hi> there was <hi>a Parliament</hi> called in <hi>that Kingdome,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:162339:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>which acted in the beginning [as this of <hi>England</hi> did] for Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; whereupon <hi>Charles</hi> their King <hi>raiſed War againſt them,</hi> and they, for the defence of themſelves, and the peoples rights and liberties, <hi>raiſed ſeveral Armies,</hi> and by force of Arms viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſubdued the <hi>King,</hi> as we have really done ours, and reſcued the <hi>Kingdom</hi> from <hi>all Prerogative Tyranny.</hi> This <hi>Spaniſh Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> did at the firſt make ſuch <hi>ſpecial Ordinances</hi> for the good of the Publique, as their very enemies ſtiled them holy and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious: And, ſaith the <hi>Chronicle,</hi> had they been duly executed, <hi>Spain</hi> had been the moſt glorious <hi>Kingdom</hi> in the world, and the ſaid <hi>King Charles,</hi> had appeared a moſt cruel and <hi>tyrannical Prince,</hi> if he had not confirmed them.</p>
            <p>But (ſaith the <hi>Chronicle</hi>) That <hi>Parliament</hi> ſpoiled all, when the Wars were ended, by falling into ambition, covetouſneſs, and faction, betraying and ſelling one another, and ſharing the Kingdoms treaſure amongſt them: And ſo notwithſtanding all their famous Acts in the beginning (they not keeping and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them, themſelves, but looking after private ends) did thereby loſe the affections of the people, deſtroyed themſelves, and betrayed their 3 victorious<note n="*" place="margin">Beware Lord Fairfnx, &amp;c.</note> Generals: <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Earl of Salvatora,</hi> the <hi>Biſhop of Samoora,</hi> and <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Padillia,</hi> with 70 of their beſt<note n="*" place="margin">Look about you, ye that are honeſt men in both Houſes.</note>
               <hi>Parliament men</hi> into the hands of their conquered King; who did forthwith put them all to death: And that <hi>Parliament</hi> (ſaith the Author) was the laſt in that <hi>Kingdom</hi> that acted for the Peoples Freedoms; ever ſince hath the whole Nation layen under inextricable bondage, tyranny, and oppreſſion. And doth not this ſeem to be written for our admonition and inſtruction? <hi>Foelix quem faciunt aliena peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula cautum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, What benefit can we the <hi>Commons of England</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by this Treaty, in caſe all be granted that is required; while the name of the <hi>Norman Conqueſt,</hi> and ſo many ſeveral ſhameful badges thereof, (as multiplicity of Laws, and they in <hi>Pedlers French,</hi> or the <hi>Norman language,</hi> ſuper-abundant vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Courts, and Officers, ſtrange ſlaviſh tenures, fealties, and ſervices,) ſuch as this Nation never before knew, do ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue? And that ſtill, after ſo much bloodſhed, and expence of treaſure, about the <hi>Militia of the Land,</hi> in whom it is original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whether in the King or People? it muſt be granted and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:162339:9"/>continued, to be in the King, and in his power and diſpoſe, at his will and pleaſure (as he hath already done) to cut our throats. Grant him this, and grant him all. Grant him but this to remain (according to his requeſt) unqueſtionably in the <hi>Crown,</hi> and his <hi>Negative Vote</hi> alſo; and grant him to be a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <hi>per ſtatutum imperpetuum,</hi> both him and his (for indeed they would be ſo likewiſe) from <hi>generation to generation.</hi> And for us now to accord, that after ſo many years (were the twenty years an hundred] he or his ſhould have the Militia again in their own hands and diſpoſe, is but, as if a man that had by a a long and ſtrong conteſt recovered his inheritance from one that had a long time illegally and injuſtly held it from him ſhould notwithſtanding for quietneſs-ſake [as fools often ſay] agree to accept of a leaſe of it, for certain years, and ſtill to grant the title to be in his adverſary, and after the expiration of thoſe years for ever to exclude himſelf and his. And this his Majeſty plainly ſhews, in propounding to leaſe the Biſhops Lands, and not to ſell them, to the end that the propriety of them may ſtill continue in the Biſhops. If we have a right in the Militia for years, why not for ever? But it is undeniable, that at this time it is abſolutely and wholy (where it was <hi>in origine</hi>) in us (the People) and in our power and diſpoſe: and why ſhould we give, or grant it, be it but for a moment, to another? In a word to grant the Kings deſire in this, would be like <hi>the hewing down Nebuchadnezzars mighty Tree, and cutting off the branches and leaves thereof: yet leaving the ſtump of the roots thereof in the earth with bands of iron and braſs.</hi> No, let us up with root and all; that there may be more remembranca of <hi>Prerogative, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronny, and Norman Bondage</hi> amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Note, that while the K. pretends a Treaty for Peace, He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends and countenanceth a War againſt us. What elſe mean his Sons and Confederates their preparations? If any ſay, It is not by his Command: I anſwer, Why doth he not prohibit or countermand it? <hi>Qui non prohibet, cum poteſt, jubet?</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
